The tsunami has completely flooded the area.
The entire area is flooded.
Please lower your use.
I can confirm.
Roger that.
Ten years after the Fukushima disaster,
scenes like these are still hard to watch.
The 2011 earthquake and tsunami devastated northeastern Japan,
killing more than 15,000,
leveling more than 120,000 homes,
and costing upwards of $200 billion in damage.
The force of the blast disagrees with the official line that the reactor itself survived.
Inconceivable.
Ten years later,
the scars of the earthquake and nuclear disaster are still visible.
Today,
the population of Fukushima Prefecture remains 180,000 less than before the triple disaster.
Vice World News traveled back to Fukushima weeks before the 10th anniversary to meet some of the people who,
despite it all,
refused to leave.
This is Namiya Town,
20 kilometers from the Daiichi nuclear power plants,
the site of the second worst nuclear accident in human history.
Before the disaster,
some 21,000 people called Namiya Town home.
Today,
the population is little more than 1,200.
We're on our way to meet Yoshizawa-san,
who owns a ranch here in Namiya Town.
And he was one of the very first residents to return to the town,
even though it was still declared unsafe.
And we want to ask him what made him take that risk,
why he returned,
and what he thinks of Namiya Town
10 years from the disaster.
Masami Yoshizawa used to be a dairy farmer.
Then radiation from the nearby nuclear plant sickened his herd.
He has 257 cows remaining.
All of them are too radioactive to consume their meat or milk.
What happened to the cows after you had to evacuated?
The deal I had to sell 330 cows was cancelled.
They told me, "don't bring them.
They said, "[the cows] are radioactive."
The boss who made the deal said it was over.
Everything was over. He told me to run.
uSv/h
Everyone within this 20 kilometer
perimeter had to evacuate immediately.
So I had to escape while all my cows were still tethered here.
Some dairy farmers left with their cows still tied up.
The animals eventually died of starvation.
They had no water, no food. The cows became mummies.
I stayed at the ranch for about a week, until March 17 or 18.
I had 330 cows to take care of.
I couldn't just evacuate immediately.
After that, the government told us to "dispose" of all
surviving livestock. That was the instructions we received.
After that, the government told us to "dispose" oall
They barricaded the area on April 22, 2011.
We couldn't get in. We couldn't take care of the cows.
Most dairy farmers had no choice
but to follow the government's orders.
All stray cows had to be captured and killed.
So within this 20 kilometer barricade,
our only options were to starve or kill our cows.
You can't go back to being a farmer,
once you've abandoned them like that.
I've been a dairy farmer for a long time,
so I've always considered myself one with the animals. I continued
to take care of them. I didn't follow the government's orders.
In one farm, mixed among all the bones,
we found one surviving cow.
It didn't leave. We were asked to rescue it, so we took it in.
It somehow survived while
all the others died or were killed.
Is this cow still alive?
Yes. There was nothing to drink because of
the power outages, so I released them all from the barn.
There were so many cows. They were
waiting for us to come back and give them food.
"A space between 'the police' and 'break through'?"
shouldn't be there. Should be "We'd come every three days
to break the barrier with our truck, and deliver the cows' food."
That's why they were able to survive.
This is from one year later. Suddenly,
these spots began to appear on the cows.
These white spots on the black Wagyu cows.
They were eating radioactive grass.
One year later, they had these spots.
Their hides and skin are both black.
But in these areas, it turned white.
One year after the disaster, 20 cows suddenly had these spots.
And these cows are still alive?
Yes.
When you treat life in this horrible way,
I think it leaves deep scars on your heart.
It's like trauma. The wounds on your heart never go away.
Using the compensation money from TEPCO,
I continued to take care of the cows.
I'm not sure how long I can keep doing this though.
I never thought about leaving this place.
This is my hometown. This is
where I'll end my life, at this farm.
This bone is from the spine of a dead cow.
These two connect like this. This is
where the stomach and intestines are.
This is out of respect for the cows.
It's a marker for their graves.
The character is called "obagyu." It's a cow
ghost. They died and came back as ghosts.
Their souls are still floating around on this farm.
The soil surrounding Yoshizawa's ranch is still contaminated by radiation,
with some locations measuring above the international safety threshold.
1.4. About one meter from the ground,
the radioactivity is 1.4 microsieverts.
This isn't good. This isn't a safe place.
How do you feel when you see these numbers?
I'm not surprised. If you put this closer to
the ground, the number goes up to 2.
Where in Namie town is the radioactivity highest?
Some places have such high readings, 6 or even 7
microsieverts. They're usually up in the mountains.
That's where a lot of radioactivity still remains.
This farm hasn't been decontaminated. This earth is the
same that was here when the nuclear power plant collapsed.
The grass contaminated by the disaster still grows here.
Everyone in Namie town has lost their roots to the town.
They were kicked out, left in the dust.
Are there people who won't ever come back?
Yes, some will never come back.
There are hardly any kids here anymore.
This was once Ukedo Elementary School.
On March 11,
2011,
the school was hit with a two-story tall wave as the tsunami moved inland.
Nearly a hundred students and teachers were in the school when disaster struck.
all escaped with their lives.
One of them was Shinichi Sato,
a former teacher.
That clock shows the time when the tsunami
caused the most damage in this area.
Inside the school, there's a circuit that controls that clock.
But when the tsunami came, it broke the circuit,
so 2.46 p.m. is when Ukedo was struck by the tsunami.
How do you feel when you see that clock?
By that time we had already escaped to the mountains.
I'm glad we weren't here. That's why our lives were saved.
But the 200 residents who were still
here then, they lost their lives to the tsunami.
It was an hour after the earthquake,
but they must've not been able to escape.
This area looks exactly like it did after the disaster struck.
They're not going to clean it up. It's been
left as the remains of the earthguake.
So they'll leave it as it is.
Yes. For 10 years, it's looked like this.
You can see how tremendously strong the waves must have been.
If you go closer, you can see the rubble
has been swept up to the ceiling.
When you visit this place, I think you can understand
how strong and destructive the waves were.
Do you want this school to remain here forever?
This is the only building still left,
in the middle of all this flat land. It's where you can
really understand what happened on that day.
I want this place to stay for the residents of this area.
How did you manage to evacuate all 98 of your students?
When the earthquake struck,
we were afraid the ground under us
would open up. Everyone gathered here.
I was still inspecting inside the school
was still inspecting inside the school
so I hadn't come downstairs yet, but
everyone followed the principal's orders.
You can't see it from here, but everyone
headed to Mount Ohira, a huge mountain.
We left the school grounds and followed
the path to the end of the rice fields,
and went up the mountain with all the children.
Shinichi Sato now teaches at a newly built school that opened three years ago to a student body of just 30 children.
I'm sure there weren't that many students
when you first came back to teach,
but did it feel sad to be teaching in
a classroom with so few students?
Before I came back, I was a part time teacher in a different
part of Fukushima. There were 30-40 students per class.
It was lively and there were so many different students.
But when I came back here, there were only two desks.
It was me and two students, in a big classroom.
It felt sort of homey, but there wasn't any of fighting,
or conflict, that's a natural part of a child's development.
Whether that's good or bad, that's difficult to say.
The number of students is increasing, but it's
nowhere near what it once was. There aren't enough students.
Most importantly, the kids can't ride
their bikes to go play after school.
There are still wild animals roaming around, After dark,
no one is out walking. And everyone comes to school by bus.
When we were kids, everyone would play in the schoolyard with
other kids. The children don't experience any of that now.
Not after the disaster. I feel sorry for them,
that they'll leave childhood without those experiences.
Were some residents afraid of radiation poisoning?
I think at the beginning some people
were concerned, like with the water.
But they've been monitoring this area closely and the
data shows it's safe, so no one's anxious anymore.
We drink the milk, the water, we even use the faucets.
And they inspect all the seafood that's caught.
I think most people living here are more or less at peace.
They don't give radiation poisoning much thought.
So is Namie town a safe place?
Well, the decommissioned buildings are still here, and with
the recent earthguake, we don't know what's going to happen.
I think things are getting calmer, to some extent,
but I don't think you can say it's totally safe.
The disaster was a decade ago.
But that doesn't mean Fukushima stopped experiencing earthquakes.
Just one day before we arrived,
a huge 7.3 quake shook the prefecture.
It left the region without power,
killed one,
and injured dozens more.
So this is the wall of the hotel that we're staying at.
And as you can see,
some of the wallpaper has come and done from a 7.3 shake that happened just a few days ago.
And as you go further down the hallway,
it gets even worse.
Here's another crack.
And further down here you can see some of the plaster that's come down from the ceiling.
Yeah,
just right here.
And the fact this happened just a few days before the 10-year passing since the triple disaster on March 11,
2011,
I think served as a reminder of just how tragic events were 10 years ago.
Despite all of this,
life is slowly returning to Namie Town.
Tsukasa Yamada was drawn back home to take part in the reconstruction efforts.
His daughter was born right after the disaster.
He sees this as a fresh start for his family.
Were you concerned for your
child's health because of the radiation?
Yeah, I think so. But while I'm concerned, I'm not doing
anything different to address it. We're just living our normal lives.
I have heard that it might have an
effect on her health once she's an adult.
So I do worry about her health as she grows up.
Have you ever experienced discrimination
because you were from Fukushima?
Yes, of course. People would say, "oh
you're from Fukushima? Is that OK?"
There were times I was treated like I was radioactive.
Where dlid you experience this?
Columbia
The first place I evacuated to was Niigata prefecture.
Columbi
My car still had Fukushima plates, so people would ask,
"you're from Fukushima?" It was very transparent.
It's like, when one recovers from the coronavirus,
people say, "Oh, that person had covid." Jonathan Vit is this okay?
So I think it's only natural that some people would pull away
when they hear Fukushima. It's a natural human reaction.
Do you have hopes and dreams
for yourself, as well as Namie town?
Yes, I do. Before the disaster, Namie town
had a population of about 20,000 people.
I hope that through our hard work,
we can return the town to what it once was.
But as the town looks to rebuild,
an ominous reminder of the dangers remain in plain sight.
The TEPCO-owned Daiichi Nuclear Plant,
which can be seen from Masami Yoshizawa's ranch.
This is it. I see it.
How many kilometers away is the plant?
In a straight line, 14 kilometers.
On March 17th, I went to the second floor and used binoculars
to see how the SDF was cleaning up the Daiichi nuclear plant.
I could see the flames. I thought, "the Self
Defense Force, the firefighters, they're all going to die."
The TEPCO employees decided to retreat, so they
escaped to the second power plant, fleeing the first one.
I had been here a week and when I saw that, I decided
that those bastards at TEPCO, I'm never going to forgive them.
When the SDF were working hard to protect us, TEPCO
ran away. I don't care, I'll spend the rest of my life fighting this plant.
I will remain against nuclear power. Until the day I die, I will
take care of these cows and fight for a world without nuclear power.
We can't sell our rice, our vegetables. We can't return home.
Our town has become Cherynobyl. Everyone, the
Fukushima nuclear disaster could be Tokyo's tomorrow.
400 Wagyu cow herders had to leave their cows and escape.
Keep fighting! For our future, for our
children, for ourselves, keep fighting!
The farmers who let their cows starve to
death don't want to see the ones that are still alive.
Because when they do, they're reminded of the past.
But I don't think they made a mistake. It was
unavoidable. At the time, they had no other choice.
They couldn't care for their cows.
So they apologized instead.
They said, "I'm sorry. To save us humans,
you have to stay here and rot / die. I'm so sorry.
That's why they can't have cows again. But they weren't wrong.
And the ones who listened and killed their herds aren't wrong either.
I'm not wrong either. There's no right
answer here. There are multiple answers.
I understand that now, 10 years later. We can't
be emotional and argue about this anymore.
We have to accept each other, understand each other.
That's what's happened, over these 10 years.
This is Futaba,
a town only 4 kilometers from the nuclear power plant,
where time seems to stand still.
This is the main street here.
Futaba is still inside what Japanese officials declared a difficult-to-return zone.
meaning radiation levels are too high to allow people to move back.
There's a term in Japanese,
shouganai,
that is often used to acknowledge conflict or pain.
The Fukushima residents we spoke to paid respect to their past in this way.
As you walk through the town of Futaba,
you can still see the remains of the triple disaster ten years ago.
The buildings haven't been replaced yet,
and the destruction serves as a reminder of the tragedies this town faced.
Even as some residents hope for a brighter future,
they live with the past because it's
Shogunai.